<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rfc version="3" category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-yoshikawa-sidrops-pqc-rpki-00" submissionType="IETF" consensus="true">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PQC for RPKI">Post-Quantum Signature Algorithm Profile and Migration Considerations for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-yoshikawa-sidrops-pqc-rpki-00" />
    <author fullname="Tomoki Yoshikawa" initials="T." surname="Yoshikawa">
      <organization>Graduate School of Informatics, Kyoto University</organization>
      <address>
        <email>segre@marokiki.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="June" day="18" />
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>SIDROPS</workgroup>
    <keyword>RPKI</keyword>
    <keyword>PQC</keyword>
    <keyword>ML-DSA</keyword>
    <keyword>SLH-DSA</keyword>
    <keyword>SIDROPS</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies an initial post-quantum signature algorithm profile and migration considerations for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI).  It profiles ML-DSA-65 as the primary candidate for an RPKI next signature algorithm suite by reusing the ML-DSA algorithm identifiers and CMS conventions defined by LAMPS.  It also describes how Certification Authorities, repository operators, and Relying Parties can evaluate and deploy a post-quantum suite while preserving the existing RPKI architecture and router-facing VRP/RTR model.</t>
      <t>This document profiles candidate post-quantum signature algorithms for RPKI certificates, CRLs, certification requests, and CMS signed objects. It is written as input to SIDROPS discussion and does not update RFC 7935 in this revision.  It does not define a new RPKI object format, a new cryptographic primitive, a new repository synchronization protocol, or a new router protocol.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The RPKI relies on digital signatures in resource certificates, CRLs, certification requests, and CMS signed objects such as manifests and Route Origin Authorizations (ROAs).  The deployed RPKI algorithm profile is based on RSA with SHA-256.  A Cryptographically Relevant Quantum Computer (CRQC) would invalidate the long-term security assumptions of RSA signatures.  RPKI therefore needs an algorithm migration path that can be tested before an emergency transition is required.</t>
      <t>The design goal of this document is conservative.  RPKI already has a well-defined architecture, repository system, validation procedure, and router interface.  This document keeps those layers intact.  PQC processing is introduced at the Certification Authority (CA), repository, CMS signed object, and Relying Party (RP) validation layers.  Routers that consume Validated ROA Payloads (VRPs) through the RPKI-Router Protocol (RTR) or local files are not expected to process PQC signatures directly.</t>
      <t>This revision is intended as a SIDROPS starting point.  It deliberately separates the protocol profile from the transition timetable and from the implementation evidence.  Where this document uses terms such as "candidate" or "evaluation", the text is identifying open engineering questions rather than declaring the final global RPKI migration plan.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="requirements-language">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" />
        <xref target="RFC8174" /> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="terminology">
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>This document uses the terminology of the RPKI architecture <xref target="RFC6480" />, the resource certificate profile <xref target="RFC6487" />, the RPKI signed object template <xref target="RFC6488" />, the RPKI algorithm agility procedure <xref target="RFC6916" />, and the RPKI algorithm profile <xref target="RFC7935" />.</t>
      <t>Current Suite:  The algorithm suite currently accepted by an RPKI implementation for production validation.  At the time of writing this is RSA-2048/SHA-256 as profiled by RFC 7935.</t>
      <t>Next Suite:  A candidate algorithm suite that is implemented and tested before it becomes the Current Suite.</t>
      <t>PQC Suite:  A Next Suite whose signature algorithm is intended to remain secure against a CRQC.</t>
      <t>Corresponding Products:  RPKI products issued under different algorithm suites that assert the same RPKI semantics.  For ROAs, this means the same set of VRPs, modulo local policy and trust anchor selection.</t>
      <t>Semantic Equivalence:  A property of two validated RPKI outputs in which their routing semantics are identical.  For ROA-derived VRPs, the comparison keys are prefix, maxLength, origin AS, and validation source or trust anchor context.</t>
      <t>Parallel Publication:  A migration technique in which a CA publishes corresponding products under both the Current Suite and the Next Suite for an extended interval.</t>
      <t>Composite Signature:  A single signature algorithm construction that combines a PQC algorithm and a traditional algorithm at the cryptographic or encoding layer.  This document does not require composite signatures for the initial RPKI PQC suite.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="scope">
      <name>Scope</name>
      <t>This document applies to RPKI resource certificates, CRLs, certification requests, manifests <xref target="RFC9286" />, ROAs <xref target="RFC9582" />, and other CMS signed objects that reuse the RPKI signed object template.</t>
      <t>This document does not specify changes to BGPsec path signatures, ASPA, RSC, router certificates, RTR, TAL formats, RRDP <xref target="RFC8182" />, rsync, or the RPKI Certificate Policy.  These topics may require companion work after the basic certificate and CMS profile is interoperable.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="design-goals">
      <name>Design Goals</name>
      <t>The profile has the following goals.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Preserve the existing RPKI architecture and repository model.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Reuse existing LAMPS PKIX and CMS encodings for PQC algorithms.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Avoid new RPKI object formats unless measurements show that simple</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>signature substitution is infeasible.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Keep routers as consumers of validated payloads, not PQC validators.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Support a prolonged Current Suite and Next Suite interval.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Make downgrade, unsupported-algorithm, and semantic-divergence cases</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>observable by RPs and operators.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Keep measurement and interoperability evidence reproducible outside the</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>protocol specification.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="algorithm-profile">
      <name>Algorithm Profile</name>
      <section anchor="current-suite">
        <name>Current Suite</name>
        <t>The Current Suite remains RSA PKCS #1 v1.5 with SHA-256 as specified by RFC 7935 until a separate transition timetable changes production RPKI policy.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="primary-next-suite">
        <name>Primary Next Suite</name>
        <t>The primary PQC Next Suite candidate defined by this document is ML-DSA-65.</t>
        <t>This revision defines ML-DSA-65 as the primary candidate implementation profile.  It does not yet require production acceptance.  An implementation experiment SHOULD process id-ml-dsa-65 in RPKI certificates and CRLs according to RFC 9881 and SHOULD report separately whether RFC 9882 CMS SignedData is supported.</t>
        <t>RPKI CAs participating in an isolated experiment MAY use ML-DSA-65 for CA certificates, EE certificates, and CRLs.  They MUST NOT publish experimental objects into a production repository or use production keys or TALs.  CMS signed objects remain an interoperability work item in this revision.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="additional-candidate-suites">
        <name>Additional Candidate Suites</name>
        <t>ML-DSA-87 MAY be implemented as a higher-security candidate, especially for experiments involving trust anchors or upper-tier CAs.  This document does not require ML-DSA-87 for basic interoperability because it produces larger objects than ML-DSA-65.</t>
        <t>SLH-DSA-SHAKE-128s and SLH-DSA-SHAKE-192s MAY be implemented for cryptographic-diversity experiments.  They are not recommended as the initial default production RPKI suite in this version because their signature sizes and signing costs are substantially higher than ML-DSA in the available measurements.</t>
        <t>Falcon/FN-DSA, MAYO, SNOVA, and HAWK are outside the mandatory path of this document.  They may be evaluated as research candidates, but they MUST NOT be treated as RPKI production algorithm suites by this document until stable PKIX and CMS profiles exist and are referenced by a future revision or separate document.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="algorithm-selection-rationale">
        <name>Algorithm Selection Rationale</name>
        <t>ML-DSA-65 is selected as the primary candidate because it has an existing FIPS signature specification <xref target="FIPS204" /> and corresponding PKIX <xref target="RFC9881" /> and CMS <xref target="RFC9882" /> algorithm identifier specifications.  It is not selected because it is always the smallest or fastest possible signature algorithm.</t>
        <t>ML-DSA-87, SLH-DSA-SHAKE-128s, and SLH-DSA-SHAKE-192s remain useful comparison points for security level, cryptographic diversity, and repository stress testing.  The SLH-DSA candidates have corresponding signature, PKIX, and CMS specifications <xref target="FIPS205" />
          <xref target="RFC9909" />
          <xref target="RFC9814" />. Falcon/FN-DSA and other additional-signature candidates may be attractive for size or performance reasons, but they are outside the mandatory path of this revision until stable PKIX and CMS profiles and RPKI validator evidence are available.</t>
        <t>Detailed measurements for key sizes, signature sizes, primitive timings, repository-size estimates, and validator probes are maintained outside this document by the experimental harness <xref target="pqc-rpki-lab" />.  Those values are implementation and environment dependent and are not protocol requirements.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="resource-certificate-and-crl-profile">
      <name>Resource Certificate and CRL Profile</name>
      <t>RPKI resource certificates and CRLs using ML-DSA MUST follow the certificate and CRL conventions for ML-DSA defined in RFC 9881.  In particular, AlgorithmIdentifier parameters for ML-DSA MUST be absent.</t>
      <t>When id-ml-dsa-65 or id-ml-dsa-87 appears in SubjectPublicKeyInfo, the subjectPublicKey BIT STRING contains the raw public key encoding defined by FIPS 204 and profiled by RFC 9881.</t>
      <t>For RPKI CA certificates, the keyUsage extension MUST remain consistent with the resource certificate profile.  A CA certificate that is used to issue certificates and CRLs requires keyCertSign and cRLSign.  An EE certificate used for an RPKI signed object requires digitalSignature and MUST NOT be used as a CA certificate.</t>
      <t>This document does not change the RPKI resource extension semantics, certificate policy OID, certificate path validation procedure, manifest processing rules, or CRL processing rules.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="cms-signed-object-profile">
      <name>CMS Signed Object Profile</name>
      <t>RPKI signed objects using ML-DSA MUST follow the CMS conventions for ML-DSA defined in RFC 9882 and the RPKI signed object template defined in RFC 6488.</t>
      <t>The signatureAlgorithm field of SignerInfo MUST contain id-ml-dsa-65 for the primary Next Suite.  AlgorithmIdentifier parameters MUST be absent.</t>
      <t>The signedAttrs element remains REQUIRED for RPKI signed objects.  It MUST include the content-type and message-digest attributes required by RFC 6488.  Other signed attributes remain restricted by the RPKI signed object template.</t>
      <t>This revision does not select a digestAlgorithms or SignerInfo digestAlgorithm value for ML-DSA.  OpenSSL 3.6.2 generated ML-DSA certificates and CRLs but its CMS CLI rejected ML-DSA signing with <tt>CMS_add1_signer:no default digest</tt>.  The correct RFC 9882 and RFC 6488 combination therefore requires implementation and interoperability evidence before normative values are specified here.</t>
      <t>The CMS eContentType and eContent for ROAs, manifests, and other RPKI signed objects are unchanged.  Validators MUST apply the object-specific validation rules after CMS signature validation exactly as they do for the Current Suite.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="manifests-roas-and-repository-processing">
      <name>Manifests, ROAs, and Repository Processing</name>
      <section anchor="implementation-evidence">
        <name>Implementation Evidence</name>
        <t>The accompanying implementation harness generated ML-DSA-65, ML-DSA-87, SLH-DSA-SHAKE-128s, and SLH-DSA-SHAKE-192s CA certificates, EE certificates, and CRLs using the OpenSSL 3.6.2 default provider.  The certificates included RFC 3779 IP address and AS resource extensions, RPKI certificate policy, Subject Information Access, basic constraints, and key usage.  Private keys were generated only in an automatically deleted temporary directory.</t>
        <t>The same OpenSSL installation did not generate ML-DSA CMS SignedData. Consequently, no RFC 6488 manifest or ROA was generated by the harness. This is an implementation limitation, not evidence that the RFC profiles are incompatible.  Routinator, rpki-client, and FORT were not installed in the measurement environment, so validator acceptance is unconfirmed.</t>
        <t>The default run did not receive a real local RPKI cache.  Repository impact values in this revision remain synthetic or literature-calibrated estimates.</t>
        <t>This document does not define new payload encodings for manifests, ROAs, or CRLs.  Repository operators MAY publish Current Suite and Next Suite products in parallel during an algorithm transition.  A repository that publishes parallel products MUST ensure that manifests and CRLs are internally consistent within each suite.</t>
        <t>During parallel publication, operators SHOULD provide a way to identify corresponding products across suites for measurement and debugging.  This identification MAY be derived from publication point structure, object names, CA hierarchy, or an implementation-specific mapping.  It is not a new on-wire RPKI object in this version.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="relying-party-behavior">
      <name>Relying Party Behavior</name>
      <t>An RP that implements this document MUST be configurable with an accepted algorithm policy.  The policy MUST be able to represent at least:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Current Suite only;</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Current Suite plus Next Suite;</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Next Suite preferred with Current Suite fallback;</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Next Suite only.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>An RP MUST reject a certificate, CRL, or signed object whose signature algorithm is not in its configured policy.  The rejection reason SHOULD be reported distinctly from syntax errors, path validation failures, manifest failures, and object-specific semantic failures.</t>
      <t>An RP that validates both Current Suite and Next Suite products SHOULD perform semantic-equivalence checks for corresponding products.  For ROAs, this check compares the resulting VRP set by prefix, maxLength, origin AS, and trust anchor context.  If the Current Suite and Next Suite produce different routing semantics, the RP SHOULD emit telemetry and SHOULD NOT silently merge the divergent outputs.</t>
      <t>This document does not require routers to support PQC.  Routers receive validated payloads through RTR or local export formats.  The RP remains the cryptographic enforcement point.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="migration-strategy">
      <name>Migration Strategy</name>
      <t>The migration strategy follows the planned, multi-year model described in RFC 6916.  This document does not define an emergency migration.</t>
      <t>A deployment that follows this document is expected to proceed through the following phases.</t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <t>Implementation readiness: CAs and RPs add support for the Next Suite in</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>non-production code paths.</t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <t>Test repositories: operators publish PQC test repositories under test</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>TALs.</t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <t>Parallel publication: selected CAs publish corresponding products under</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>the Current Suite and the Next Suite.</t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <t>RP measurement: RPs validate both suites and report validation time,</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>repository size, failure modes, and semantic equivalence.</t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <t>PQC-preferred operation: RPs prefer the Next Suite while retaining the</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>Current Suite for a limited period.</t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <t>Classical retirement: a separate transition timetable defines the</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>twilight date and withdrawal of the old suite.</t>
      <t>This document assumes the top-down migration constraint of RFC 6916 for production deployment.  Experiments involving partial parent migration, partial child migration, or mixed unsupported validator deployment are useful for failure analysis, but they are not declared valid production transition states by this revision.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="implementation-status">
      <name>Implementation Status</name>
      <t>This section records the status of known implementations of the protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in <xref target="RFC7942" />.  It is intended to assist IETF discussion and is to be removed before publication as an RFC.</t>
      <t>An experimental repository, pqc-rpki-lab, was used to evaluate this proposal.  The implementation status at the time of this draft is:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Static algorithm metadata: implemented.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Primitive benchmark using existing libraries: implemented.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Synthetic repository impact estimator: implemented.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Local cache size collector: implemented.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>VRP semantic equivalence checker: implemented for CSV/JSON fixtures.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Validator probes: implemented, but Routinator, rpki-client, and FORT</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>were not installed in the test environment.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>RFC-profiled PQC CA certificates, EE certificates, and CRLs: generated</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>with OpenSSL 3.6.2 for ML-DSA and SLH-DSA.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>PQC CMS SignedData: unsupported by the tested OpenSSL CMS CLI, which</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>returned <tt>CMS_add1_signer:no default digest</tt>.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Manifest and ROA generation: not completed because PQC CMS signing and an</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>existing payload generator were unavailable.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Multi-validator interoperability using real PQC RPKI objects: future work.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>The highest-priority implementation gap is an RFC 9882-capable CMS path and an existing MFT/ROA payload generator.  The second highest-priority gap is independent validator behavior for complete objects.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The purpose of this document is to reduce the risk that RPKI signatures become forgeable in the presence of a CRQC.  It does not solve CA compromise, repository compromise, operational misissuance, BGP policy mistakes, or route leaks.</t>
      <t>Downgrade attacks are a primary concern during a long transition.  An RP that supports both Current Suite and Next Suite products MUST make its algorithm acceptance policy explicit.  It MUST NOT silently accept a Current Suite product as equivalent to a missing or invalid Next Suite product when local policy requires the Next Suite.</t>
      <t>Parallel publication introduces the possibility of semantic divergence. For example, the RSA branch and the PQC branch might contain different ROA payloads, stale manifests, or different CRL state.  Validators SHOULD detect and report these cases rather than silently selecting one branch without operator visibility.</t>
      <t>Larger public keys, signatures, certificates, CRLs, and CMS objects can increase repository transfer size, local cache size, manifest size, and validation time.  Implementations SHOULD enforce resource limits and telemetry for object size, number of objects, validation time, and memory use.  Operators SHOULD evaluate RRDP snapshot and delta sizes before large-scale deployment.</t>
      <t>ML-DSA uses randomized signing by default.  CA implementations and HSMs MUST use cryptographically appropriate randomness and SHOULD follow the operational guidance in RFC 9881 and RFC 9882.  Deterministic signing is not preferred for platforms where side-channel or fault attacks are a concern.</t>
      <t>Algorithm confusion is possible if AlgorithmIdentifier parameters, SignerInfo digestAlgorithm, CMS signed attributes, or certificate SubjectPublicKeyInfo encodings are inconsistently handled.  Implementations MUST reject malformed AlgorithmIdentifier encodings and MUST follow the parameter rules of the referenced LAMPS specifications.</t>
      <t>Composite signatures may protect against failures in one component algorithm, but they also introduce additional encoding, policy, and interoperability complexity.  This document treats composite signatures as future work until the corresponding LAMPS specifications <xref target="I-D.ietf-lamps-pq-composite-sigs" />
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-lamps-cms-composite-sigs" /> and RPKI-specific policy questions are stable.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document requests no new IANA allocations in its current form.  The ML-DSA and SLH-DSA algorithm identifiers are reused from existing PKIX and CMS specifications.  If a future revision defines an RPKI-specific algorithm-suite registry or new telemetry identifiers, this section will be updated.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="open-issues">
      <name>Open Issues</name>
      <t>The following issues require additional SIDROPS discussion and implementation evidence.  In particular, this draft should not strengthen ML-DSA-65 requirement language until complete RFC 6488 PQC objects are generated and major validator behavior is measured.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Whether ML-DSA-65 should be mandatory-to-implement for RPs and CAs.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Whether ML-DSA-87 is needed for trust anchors or upper-tier CAs.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Whether SLH-DSA should remain only a diversity experiment.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Whether composite signatures are needed for RPKI, or whether parallel</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>publication is operationally sufficient.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Whether Null Scheme-like signed-object reductions</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        <xref target="I-D.doesburg-sidrops-nullscheme" /> should be considered separately from the initial signature-algorithm profile.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>How to define a transition timetable and readiness metrics for RPKI</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>deployment.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Whether semantic-equivalence checking should be mandatory during the</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>parallel-publication phase.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>How to handle PQC unsupported validators in mixed deployments.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Whether TAK, ASPA, RSC, and BGPsec should be covered by this document or</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>by separate companion documents.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>How RRDP snapshot and delta limits should be operationally assessed for</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>larger objects.</t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <t>Whether any RPKI-specific object naming, repository layout, or manifest</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>conventions are needed to map corresponding products across suites.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8174">
        <front>
          <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC6480">
        <front>
          <title>An Infrastructure to Support Secure Internet Routing</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6480" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC6487">
        <front>
          <title>A Profile for X.509 PKIX Resource Certificates</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6487" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC6488">
        <front>
          <title>Signed Object Template for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6488" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC6916">
        <front>
          <title>Algorithm Agility Procedure for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6916" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC7935">
        <front>
          <title>The Profile for Algorithms and Key Sizes for Use in the Resource Public Key Infrastructure</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7935" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8182">
        <front>
          <title>The RPKI Repository Delta Protocol (RRDP)</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8182" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9286">
        <front>
          <title>Manifests for the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9286" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9582">
        <front>
          <title>A Profile for Route Origin Authorizations (ROAs)</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9582" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9814">
        <front>
          <title>Use of the SLH-DSA Signature Algorithm in the Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS)</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9814" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9881">
        <front>
          <title>Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure -- Algorithm Identifiers for ML-DSA</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9881" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9882">
        <front>
          <title>Use of the ML-DSA Signature Algorithm in the Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS)</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9882" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC9909">
        <front>
          <title>Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure -- Algorithm Identifiers for SLH-DSA</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9909" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="FIPS204">
        <front>
          <title>Module-Lattice-Based Digital Signature Standard</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="FIPS" value="204" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="FIPS205">
        <front>
          <title>Stateless Hash-Based Digital Signature Standard</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="FIPS" value="205" />
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <reference anchor="RFC7942">
        <front>
          <title>Improving Awareness of Running Code: The Implementation Status Section</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7942" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-lamps-pq-composite-sigs">
        <front>
          <title>Composite ML-DSA for use in X.509 Public Key Infrastructure</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-lamps-pq-composite-sigs" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-lamps-cms-composite-sigs">
        <front>
          <title>Composite ML-DSA for use in Cryptographic Message Syntax</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-lamps-cms-composite-sigs" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="I-D.doesburg-sidrops-nullscheme">
        <front>
          <title>Null Scheme for Signed Objects in the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI)</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-doesburg-sidrops-nullscheme" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="pqc-rpki-lab" target="https://github.com/marokiki/pqc-rpki-lab/releases/tag/draft-yoshikawa-sidrops-pqc-rpki-00">
        <front>
          <title>pqc-rpki-lab experimental harness</title>
          <author fullname="Reference Editor" />
          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="acknowledgements">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The author thanks the SIDROPS and LAMPS communities for the specifications and implementation work that make this experiment possible.  Further acknowledgements will be added as the draft receives review.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>